Inventory of the Nigerian Pamphlets and Other Publications Collected by Simon Ottenberg
Hoover Institution Library
Nigerian Pamphlets and Other Publications Collected by Simon Ottenberg
1904-1967 (bulk 1940-1965)
DT515.8 .E13 N68
Ottenberg, Simon (collector)
18 microfilm reels (2.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Library Stanford, California 94305-6010
Pamphlet and serial publications from Nigeria, particularly the Eastern Region, relating to Nigerian culture, history, literature, and politics. Includes works written by people of Ibo background and Onitsha Market Literature.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Library after 1970.
Related Materials
Simon Ottenberg Papers, Northwestern University Library
Biographical/Historical Note
Anthropologist Simon Ottenberg was a faculty member at the University of Washington, Seattle, from 1955 to 1991. He specialized in West Africa, particularly southeastern Nigeria, and is noted for his knowledge of African art. He received his PhD from Northwestern University in 1957.
Scope and Content of Collection
Many of the pamphlets assembled by Ottenberg are known collectively as Onitsha Market Literature. Often written in pidgin English or Creole, these booklets were popular literature and have become an important reflection of the social lives and customs of Nigeria at midcentury. Although collections of Onitsha Market Literature are available elsewhere (for example, University of Indiana has 170 titles, the University of Kansas lists 101 titles [21 digitized], and the Digital Library of the Caribbean had digitized 21), this microfilm collection presents a wide number of otherwise unavailable or difficult-to-obtain titles.
The 343 publications in this collection are chiefly of Nigerian origin, although a few items of interest published elsewhere are included. They include a large number of works published in the old Eastern Region of Nigeria and written by people of Ibo background. Ottenberg collected them while conducting field research in Nigeria in 195253, 195960, and during a visit there in the summer of 1966.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series: (1) Serials; (2) How-to-do-it booklets; (3) Literature; (4) History, culture, language; and (5) Politics and social change.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Igbo (African people); Nigeria, Eastern--History; Nigeria--History
Collection Contents
- Serials, 1944-1966. (Reel 1-4)
  These materials were collected by the anthropologist, Simon Ottenberg, in the course of carrying out field research in Nigeria in 1952-53, 1959-60, and during a visit to Nigeria in the summer of 1966. The publications are mainly of Nigerian origin, although a few items of interest published elsewhere have been included. The pamphlets and other materials appeared mainly between 1940 and 1965, although a few later items have been added. The collection concentrates on works published in the old Eastern Region of Nigeria, and written by people of Ibo background. 64 items. Arranged alphabetically by title, African Historian to Western Equatorial Africa Church Magazine.
  - Key: Title. Publisher. Author. Issue No.[when known]. Publication date.
  - The African Historian, Journal of the Historical Society, University of Ife, Ibadan. Vol. 2, No. 1., May 1966 (Reel 1)
  - "Afroculutre". Magazine of the Society for the Promotion of African Culture, University College, Ibadan. Vol. 2, Vol 3., April 1957, April 1958 (Reel 1)
  - Alumnus. Journal of the National Alumni Association of the University of Nigeria, Nsukka. Vol. 1, No. 1., June 1966 (Reel 1)
  - The Beacon. Official Organ of the Students' Union, University of Ibadan, Ibadan, Nigeria., May 1966 (Reel 1)
  - The Bronze. Official Organ of the Students' Union, University of Ife, Ibadan. Vol. 1, No. 4., May 1966 (Reel 1)
  - Eastern Region Development. Eastern Region Development Corporation, Enugu. Vol. 1, No. 1, 3-4, Vol 2, No. 5-7, Vol. 3, No. 8-10 Vol. 4, No. 13., Oct.- Dec. 1956-Oct. 1960 (Reel 1)
  - The Ex-Solider. Journal of the Nigerian Ex-Servicemen's Welfare Association, Lagos. Vol. 1, No.1., March 1959 (Reel 1)
  - Farm and Forest. The Forest Department, Nigeria. Vol. 5, No. 4. Vol. 6, No. 3 Vol. 7, No. 1., Dec. 1944-1952 (Reel 1)
  - Farm and Forest. The Forest Department, Nigeria. Vol. 7, No.2, Vol. 8, No. 1-2, Vol. 9, No. 1, Vol. 10 and Vol. 11., Dec. 1944-1952 (Reel 2)
  - The Muse. Official Magazine of the English Association, University of Nigeria, Nsukka. Vol. 3, No. 3., April 1966 (Reel 2)
  - Niger News. C.M.S. Bookshops, Port Harcourt. Vol. 12, No. 10, Vol. 12 No. 11., Oct. -Dec., 1951 (Reel 2)
  - Nigeria. Annual Report on Antiquities Government Printer, Lagos [Annual Report of the Antiquities Branch] [Annual Report of the Antiquities Service], 1947-1948, 1949-1951, 1951-1956 (Reel 2)
  - The Nigeria Business Review. Onitsha., Nov. 1955, April 1959, Oct. 15, 1959 (Reel 2)
  - Nigeria Digest. Public Relations Office, Lagos. Vol. 1, No. 7., April 1905 (Reel 2)
  - Nigeria Year Book. A 'Daily Times' Publication. Lagos., 1952, 1953, 1959 (Reel 2)
  - Nigeria Year Book. A 'Daily Times' Publication. Lagos., May 1905 (Reel 3)
  - The Nigerian Teacher. Education Department Quarterly No. 6 No. 40, No. 41., June 1950, July 1959, Dec. 1959 (Reel 3)
  - The Torch. Magazine of the Thinkers Group of the University College, Ibadan. Vol. 1, No. 3., May 1960 (Reel 3)
  - The University Herald Quarterly Magazine of the Undergraduates of the University College, Ibadan. Vol. 1, No. 1,3, Vol. 2, No. 2,3, Vol. 3, No. 1,2, Vol. 4, No. 1-3, Vol. 5, No. 1,2., April 1948-Jan. 1953 (Reel 3)
  - The University Voice. Official Organ of the Students' Union of the University College, Ibadan. Vol.1, No. 1., Sept. 1952 (Reel 4)
  - WALA News. Bulletin of the West African Library Association, Lagos. Vol. 2, No. 2., June 1955 (Reel 4)
  - The West African Christian. Sudan Interior Mission. Jos. Vol. 1, No. 3., Aug.-Sept. 1948 (Reel 4)
  - Western Equatorial Africa. Church Magazine. Newcastle Upon Tyne. 56 New Issue 504., Sept.-Oct. 1951 (Reel 4)
- How-to-do-it booklets, 1953-1961, undated. (Reel 4)
  Mainly published in Onitsha. 14 items. Arranged alphabetically by author, Ndaeyo to Ude.
  - Key: Title. Publisher. Author. Issue No.[when known]. Publication date.
  - Ndaeyo, J. The Little Things That Matter. Rev. Goodwill Press, Port Harcourt. 2nd edition, Sept. 1953 (Reel 4)
  - Njoku. Life Turns Man Up and Down. Money and Girls Turn Man Up and Down. All Star Printers, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Njoku. How to Marry a Good Girl and Live in Peace with Her. Chinyelu Printing press, Ontisha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Nkwoh, Marius. The Sorrows of Man. International Press, Aba., Aug. 1953 (Reel 4)
  - Nnani, F.C. Never Lose Hope. Varsity Press, Onitsha., 1961 (Reel 4)
  - Okonkwo, R. No Money, Much Expenses, Enemies and Bad Friends Kill a Man (The Way to Avoid Poverty). New Era Printers, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Okonkwo, R. Never Trust All That Love You. Popular Printing Press, Onitsha. 4th edition, undated (Reel 4)
  - Olisa, Okenwa. How to Live Bachelor's Life and Girl's Life Without Much Mistakes, by the Strong man of the Pen. New Era Printers, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Olisa, Okenwa. Money Hard to Get But Easy to Spend. New Era Press., undated (Reel 4)
  - Olisa, Okenwa. How to Live Better Life and Help Yourself. All Star Printers, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Olisah, S.O.Drunkards Believe Bar as Heaven. Chinyelu Printing Press, Onitsha. [Note: Okenwa Olisa, Okenwa Olisah and S. O. Olisah appear to be the same writer., undated (Reel 4)
  - Onuoha, C.N. Moneyhard. Advice and Comfort Book to You All. Fenu Press, Port Harcourt., undated (Reel 4)
  - Moneyhard. [Psued.]. The Way to Help Life. Education Mission Press, Aba., undated (Reel 4)
  - Ude, A.O. The Nigerian Bachelor's Guide. Ude's Publishing Company, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
- Literature, 1948-1966, undated. (Reel 4-7)
  Includes some of the so-called ""Onitsha"" chapbooks. For background information see Donatus I. Nwoga, ""Onitsha Market Literature,"" Transition, 19, 1965, 26-33; Nancy J. Schmidt, ""Nigeria: Fiction for the Average Man,"" Africa Report, August 1965, 39-41, Eugene de Benko, ""Onitsha Market Literature in the Michigan State University Library,"" African Urban Notes Vol. 2 No. 2, 12-1363 items. Arranged alphabetically by author, Achebe to Uba. Includes some Onitsha Market Literature.
  - Key: Title. Publisher. Author. Issue No.[when known]. Publication date.
  - Achebe, Chinua. The Sacrificial Egg and Other Short Stories. Etudo Limited, Onitsha., April 1962 (Reel 4)
  - Adekanmbi, E.O. The Adventures of Babinton Thunder. Ore-Ofe Press, Ile-Ife., 1957 (Reel 4)
  - The African Writer. Journal of African Authors' Association of Nigeria. Etudo Limited, Onitsha. No. 1, August 1962 (Reel 4)
  - Ajokuh, Ugochukwu Emam. The Chains of Love. Atlantic Printers, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Akpabot, Samuel. Masters of the Music - Poems -. Arthur H. Stockwell Limited, Ilfracombe, Devon., undated (Reel 4)
  - Albert, Miller O. Rosemary and the Taxi Driver. Chinyelu Printing Press, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Albert, Miller O. Saturday Night Disappointment. Chinyelu Printing Press, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Alio, Emma Obiora N. Charlie and the River of Times. Mbidokwu Printing Press, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Anya, Emman U. Wretched Orphan. Tabensi Printing Press, Onitsha., undated (Reel 4)
  - Anya, Emman U. She Died in the Bloom of Youth. International Press, Aba., undated (Reel 4)
  - Anya, Udegbunem. Matter of Life and Death. International Press, Aba. [Note: probably the same as Emman U. Anya], undated (Reel 4)
  - Anya, Udegbunem. One Love Forever. Progress Printing Works, Onitsha, 1959 (Reel 5)
  - Benham, Martin (ed.) Nigerian Student Verse, 1959. Ibadan University Press, 1960 (Reel 5)
  - Egemonye, J.N.C. Broken Engagement. Delta Printing Press, Aba, undated (Reel 5)
  - Egemonye, J.N.C. Disaster in the Realms of Love. Central Printing Press, Onitsha., undated (Reel 5)
  - Ekwensi, C.O.D. When Love Whispers. Chuks, Lagos., 1948 (Reel 5)
  - Ekwensi, C.O.D. The Leopord's Claw. Longmans, Green and Co. London, Lantern Library., 1950 (Reel 5)
  - Epelle, E.M.T. The Trial of King Jaja. Literary Book Company, Enugu., 1959 (Reel 5)
  - Speedy Eric [psued]. Mabel The Sweet Honey That Poured Away. A. Onwudiwe and Sons, Onitsha., undated (Reel 5)
  - Ezedinma, Sidney. The Modern Prodigal Son. International Press, Aba., 1958 (Reel 5)
  - Giwa, S.B. The Trial of Mr. Mosquito and Mr. Fly. Salako Press, Ibadan., 1957 (Reel 5)
  - Iguh, Thomas. The Sorrows of Love. A. Onwudiwe and Sons. Onitsha., undated (Reel 5)
  - Iguh, Thomas. Alice in the Romance of Love (A Drama from West Africa). Providence Printing Press, Onitsha., undated (Reel 5)
  - Lasekan, Akinola. The Nigerian Joker. Ribway Printing Press, Lagos 2nd impression, September1949 (Reel 6)
  - Madumere, Adele. Love is Infallibel. Amacs Printing Press, Port Harcourt, 1955 (Reel 6)
  - Maimo, Sankie. I am Vindicated. Ibadan University Press, 1959 (Reel 6)
  - Maxwell, Highbred. Our Modern Lady's Characters Towards Boys. Chinyelu Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 6)
  - Mesigo, Clem E. Mesigo's Travels. Part III. Progress Printing Works Onitsha, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ngbanti, Jackson B. So Great is My Tradegy. Varsity Printing Press, Onitsha [at least partly autobiographical], undated (Reel 6)
  - Nkwocha, Sylvester Kingsley. The "Young Rascal." Ofomatas' Press, Aba, undated (Reel 6)
  - Nnama, Bedford. Still Alive Yet Buried. African Literature Bureau, Onitsha, United Brothers Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 6)
  - Nnani, Francis Christopher. The Amazing Lovers. Varsity Bookshop, Onitsha, undated (Reel 6)
  - Nnani, Francis Christopher. Should We Love the Painted Sepulchre? Varsity Publishing Company, Onitsha, undated (Reel 6)
  - Nwankwo, Gilbert. Tragic Love and the Woman From Nowhere. Ofomatas' Press, Aba, undated (Reel 6)
  - Nwosu, Cletus Givson. Miss Cordelia in the Romance of Destiny. Continental Press, Port Harcourt, undated (Reel 6)
  - Obikwelu, G.N. Pendant Smiles. Freeman's Press, Enugu, undated (Reel 6)
  - Obioha, Raphael I.M. Beauty is Trouble. Chinyelu Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 6)
  - Odili, Edmund. The Mystery of the Missing Sandals. Wese Region Literature Committee, Ife-Olu Printing Works, Lagos 2nd edition, 1953 (Reel 6)
  - Ofoma, B.N. Loving Spree. Ufondu Press, Aba, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogali, Ogali A. Mr. Rabbit is Dead (A Drama). Okeudo and Sons Printing Press, Aba, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogali, Ogali A. Okeke the Magician (A Novel). Okeudo and Sons Printing Press, Aba, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogali, Ogali A. Eddy the Coal-City Boy (A Novel). Zik Enterprises Ltd. Enugu, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogali, Ogali A. Veronica My Daughter (A Drama). Appolos Brothers Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogali, Ogali A. Adelabu (A Drama). God's Will Printing Press, Aba, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogali, Ogali A. Patrice Lumumba (A Drama). Tabensi Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogali, Ogali A. Long Long Ago (A Novel). Omaliko and Sons, Enugu, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogu, H.O. Why Women Have No Trust in Men. Confidence Printing Press, Aba, undated (Reel 6)
  - Ogu, H.O. Rose Only Loved My Money. Treasure Press, Aba, undated (Reel 7)
  - Ogu, H.O. Etim-Udo and Adiaha. In the Pool of Adventure God's Will. Printing Press, Aba, undated (Reel 7)
  - Oji, B.A. and Nwako, C.N. Akonye (The Piper). International Press, Aba, 1953 (Reel 7)
  - Okeke, Alex Obiorah. I'll Rather Break My Sword and Die (A Drama). All Star Printers, Onitsha, undated (Reel 7)
  - Okwesa, Anthony A. The Strange Death of Israel Njemanze. Tabensi Printing Press, Onitsha, 1955 (Reel 7)
  - Oleyede, S.P. The Trial of Hitler (A Play). International Press, Aba, undated (Reel 7)
  - Olisah, Okenwa. Dangerous Man Vagabond Versus Princess. New Era Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 7)
  - Olisah, Okenwa. The Half-Educated Court Messenger. General Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 7)
  - Onwudiegwu, J. Kenddys. The Miracles of Loves Gebo and Brothers. Onitsha, 1965 (Reel 7)
  - Mac-Donald, Ayo. [pseudo. For Ikwudili Orizu] The Mirror of Life. New Era Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 7)
  - Stephen, Felix N. How Tshomber and Mobutu Regretted After the Death of Lumumba. Njoku and Sons, Onitsha, undated (Reel 7)
  - Stephen, Felix N. How to Get a Lady in Love and Romance with Her, How Ugochukwu Got Caroline in Love. Njoku and Sons, Onitsha, undated (Reel 7)
  - Stephen, Felix N. Lack of Money Is Not Lack of Sense. Chinyelu Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 7)
  - Stephen, Felix N. The Life Story of Boys and Girls. Chinyelu Printing Press, Onitsha, undated (Reel 7)
  - Uba, E. The Broken Heart (A Novel). Saco Press, Enugu, undated (Reel 7)
  - Uba, E. Romance in a Nutshell (A Novel). Union Printing Press, Enugu, undated (Reel 7)
- History, culture, language, 1904-1967, undated (bulk 1940-1965). (Reel 7-12, 16)
  116 items. Arranged alphabetically by author in two groups, Achara to Wolff (reels 7-12) and Eze to Utchaey (reel 16).
  - Key: Title. Publisher. Author. Issue No.[when known]. Publication date.
  - Achara, D.N. Ala Bingo Longmans, Green and Co., London. 3rd edition., 1950 (Reel 7)
  - Ademakinwa, J. A. Ife, Cradle of the Yoruba Pacific Printing Works, Lagos. Vol. 1-2., undated (Reel 7)
  - Aguda, T. Akinola. The Marriage Law of Nigeria. Mustard Printers, Ibadan., 1966 (Reel 7)
  - Ajayi, J.F.A. Milestones in Nigerian History. Ibadan University Press., 1962 (Reel 8)
  - Alagoa, E.J. The Akassa Raid, 1895. Ibadan University Press., 1960 (Reel 8)
  - Alutu, John O. A Groundwork of Nnewi History. E.N.I.S. Press, Enugu., 1963 (Reel 8)
  - Amamihe. Central Igo News Magazine. Education Department, Nigeria Vol. 2 no. 1 Vol. 2 no. 3 Vol. 2 no.4., March 1951, September 1951, December 1951 (Reel 8)
  - Amangala, G.I. Short History of Ijaw. Ikiess Press, Port Harcourt., undated (Reel 8)
  - Anedoh, Josephat U. Nigeria Native Stories. Appolos Brothers Press, Onitsha 2nd edition., 1964 (Reel 8)
  - Anisiobi, G.N. Ibo Numeration. Oluseyi Printing Press, Kano 1st edition., 1952 (Reel 8)
  - Anon. Akwukwo Ukwe N'Asusu Ibo [Hymns in the Ibo Language]. Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, London., 1904 (Reel 8)
  - Anon. Short Life of Bishop Shanahan, C.S. Sp. Holy Ghost Fathers, Onitsha Archdiocese. A. Brown and Sons Limited, Hull., undated (Reel 8)
  - Anon. Crowther: Slave and Bishop. Church Missionary Society, London., 1949 (Reel 8)
  - Anon. Igbo Syllabus for Infant and Primary Classes. C.M.S. Press, Port Harcourt., undated (Reel 8)
  - Anon. [Possibly F.C. Ogabalu]. Igbo Syllabus for General Certificate of Education, West African School Certificate, High Elementary Certificate. Varsity Bookshop, Onitsha., undated (Reel 8)
  - Anon. Okigwe. Ife-Olu Printing Works, Lagos., 1951 (Reel 8)
  - Anon. Eastern Nigeria History Research Scheme University of Ibadan Press., undated (Reel 8)
  - Anon. They Were Cleansed, 1928-1958. The Thirtieth Anniversary Report of the Itu Leper Colony n.p., undated (Reel 8)
  - Asanye, A.M. Outlines of Nigerian History. Goodwill Printing Press, Port Harcourt., August1953 (Reel 8)
  - Biobaku, S.O. The Origin of the Yoruba. The First Lugard Lectures, 1955. Federal Information Service for the Nigerian Broadcasting Service, Lagos. (Reel 8)
  - Blocksma, Mary (editor). Traditions in Eastern Nigeria. Essays and Stories by Nigerian Students, n.p. [Enugu, circa 1966]. (Reel 8)
  - Blount, Roswell C. Report on the Nsukka Young Farmers' Scheme. Faculty of Agriculture, University of Nigeria, Nsukka., June1965 (Reel 8)
  - Blount, Roswell C. Nsukka Young Farmer Club Scheme. A Report of the Scheme's First Year and Recommendations for Future Work, Nsukka., May1963 (Reel 8)
  - Blount, Roswell C. and Attah, Efiong Ben. A Brief History of the Nsukka Area. Unversity of Nigeria, Nsukka., June1963 (Reel 8)
  - Brady, Michael [pseud.]. Our Pioneers. Crownbird Series, Public Relations Department, Lagos, Crownbird Publication. Two parts. No. 4,6., undated (Reel 8)
  - Chidia, Godwin Paul. Her Evening Tales. Goodwill Press, Port Harcourt., undated (Reel 9)
  - Chukwura, C. Okobi. A Short History of Eastern Motor Transport Workers’ Union, Nigeria. International Press, Aba., circa 1952 (Reel 9)
  - [Dennis, Archdeacon (T.J.)]. Dictionary of Ibo Language. English-Ibo. Church Missionary Society Bookshop, Lagos., 1923 (Reel 9)
  - Dennis, T.J. Ibo-English Vocabulary to the Akwukwo-Ogugu Ibo or Union Ibo Reader. James Townsend and Sons, Exeter, England., undated (Reel 9)
  - Dike, K. Onwuka. Origins of the Niger Mission, 1841-1891. Ibadan University Press for the C.M.S. Niger Mission., 1957 (Reel 9)
  - Dosumu, Gbadebo. “Queen of Shebba” [sic], “Balkis,” “Eteye,” “Makeda,” “Sungbo,” Wife of King Solomon. Dosumu Brothers Press, Ibadan., 1955 (Reel 9)
  - Douglas, A.C. Niger Memories, by ""Nemo"" (A.C. Douglas). James Townsend and Sons, Exeter, England., undated (Reel 9)
  - Ekeghe, Ogbonna O. A Short History of Abiriba. International Press, Aba., undated (Reel 9)
  - Ekpo, Mbekke E. Efik and English Phrase Book. Goodwill Press, Port Harcourt., undated (Reel 9)
  - Ekwensi, C.O.D. Ikolo the Wrestler and other Ibo Tales. Thomas Nelson and Sons, London., undated (Reel 9)
  - Epelle, E.M.T. The Church in the Niger Delta. Niger Delta Diocese. C.M.S. Press, Port Harcourt., 1955 (Reel 9)
  - Eze, K.C. The Life and Works of African Leaders and the Death of Abubakar, Bello, Akintola and Okotie Eboh and the World Current Affairs. Njoku and Sons Bookshop. Onitsha, Nigeria. No. 17., undated (Reel 16)
  - Eze, Kingsley. Our Interesting Ibo Natives Laws and Customs. New Era Printers, Onitsha., undated (Reel 9)
  - Emejulu, L.M.E. A Brief History of Railway Workers Union. Ribway Printing Press, Lagos., undated (Reel 9)
  - Fox, A.J. Uzuakoli. A Short History. Oxford University Press, London., 1964 (Reel 9)
  - Gwam, L.C. Great Nigerians – First Series. A Daily Times Publication, Lagos., 1967 (Reel 9)
  - Henderson, Richard N., Henderson, Helen Kreider. An Outline of Traditional Onitsha Ibo Socialization. Institute of Education, University of Ibadan. Occasional Publication No. 5., 1966 (Reel 9)
  - Ijere, M.O. Nsu Past and Present. University of Nigeria, Nsukka., 1965 (Reel 9)
  - Ijere, M.O. Survey of Agricultural Conditions in Nsukka. Umeh Press, Onitsha., 1965 (Reel 9)
  - Juwe, S.M. The Western Ibo People and the Coming Days. Goodwill Press, Port Harcourt., August1953 (Reel 9)
  - Ike, Akwaelumo. The Origin of the Ibos. Silent Prayer Home Press, Aba. 2nd edition., 1951 (Reel 9)
  - Ike, Akwaelumo. Great Men of Ibo Land. Clergyman Printing Press, Aba., 1952 (Reel 9)
  - Livingstone, W.P. Dr. Hitchcock of Uburu. Foreign Mission Committee of the United Free Church of Scotland, Edinburgh., 1920 (Reel 10)
  - McFarlan, Donald M. Cross River Tales. Thomas Nelson and Sons, London. Vol. 1-2., undated (Reel 10)
  - Maduekwe, Joseph C. Omekam. Ofomatas' Press, Aba., undated (Reel 10)
  - Mars, J.A. and Tooley, E.M. The Kudeti Book of Yoruba Cookery. C.M.S. Bookshop, Lagos. 7th edition., 1948 (Reel 10)
  - [Meek, C.K.] Report on Social and Political Organization in the Owerri Division. Government Printer, Lagos., 1933 (Reel 10)
  - Nigeria, Eastern Region. Igbo Syllabus for Infant and Junior Primary Classes. Government Printer, Enugu., undated (Reel 10)
  - Nigeria. Information Division, Federal Ministry of Research and Information. Preserving the Past. The Nigerian Museum and its Art Treasures. Lagos., undated (Reel 10)
  - Nigeria Union of Teachers. A Primer on Igbo Etiquette. Longmans, Green and Co. London, new impression., 1951 (Reel 10)
  - Nwafor, John O. Ilu Okwu Igbo Nke Abo. Nwafor and Sons, Aba. [Enlargement and Revision of Ibo Idioms and Proverbs, 1955 edition]., undated (Reel 10)
  - Nwana, Pita. Omenuko si na aka. Atlantic Press, London., undated (Reel 10)
  - Oduche, Okwudinka Nwoye. Life History of Ogbuefi Oduche Akunwata Akamelu. Ezeana Press, Enugu., 1951 (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. The Book of Igbo Proverbs. Varsity Bookshop,Onitsha., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. The Dictionary of Igbo Idioms. Part I. Varsity Bookshop, Onitsha., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Aku, Ahu Ichere Ya. Being Best Story Entries in a Series of Igbo Story Prize Competitions. By the Society For Promoting Igbo Language and Culture, Nigeria African Literature Bureau Varsity Bookshop, Onitsha., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Igbo-English Dictionary. African Literature Bureau Varsity Bookshop, Onitsha., 1959 (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Igbo Idioms (The Dictionary of Igbo Idioms). University Publishing Company, Onitsha. 2nd edition., 1966 (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. An Investigation into the New Ibo Orthography. Goodwill Press, Port Harcourt., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Ilu-Igbo Banyere Madu. Society for Promoting Ibo Language and Culture, Nkwerre, Orlu., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F Chidozie. Igba-Oru na Otu Esi Kwusi Ya (Slave Trade and its Abolition). Society for Promoting Ibo Language, Mbidokwu Press, Onitsha., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Mbediogu. Varsity Publishing Company, Onitsha., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Ndi Nzoputa Africa. Dr. Nnamdi Azikiwe. Dr. Kwame Nkruma [sic]. Varsity Publishing Company, Onitsha, reprint., 1956 (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Niger Tales. Book One. African Literature Bureau Varsity Bookshops, Onitsha., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Nmoo Nmoo. Igbo Fairy Tales. University Publishing Company, Onitsha., undated (Reel 10)
  - Ogbalu, F. Chidozie. Nza Na Obu (Ibo Story Book). African Literature Bureau., undated (Reel 11)